Dr. Zafar Saeed

Assistant Professor, UCP, Lahore, Pakistan

Contact Information

Faculty of Information Technology, University of Central Punjab, Lahore

Tel#: +92-42-35880007 Ext: 133 e-mail: zafar.saeed@ucp.edu.pk

Career Objectives

I aim to explore the area of my research interest by applying my educational and professional experience so that, I can contribute in creating, organizing and utilizing the knowledge to improve productivity and efficiency of the institution.

Education

2013-2020	Ph.D. (Computer Science) , Quaid-i-Azam University, Islamabad, Pakistan Thesis: Detecting Unspecified Events on Twitter
2007-2010	M.Phil (Computer Science), Quaid-i-Azam University, Islamabad, Pakistan. Thesis: Usable Layout for Scientific Documents to Support Online Reading
2003-2007	BS(Computer Science), Balochistan University of Information Technology and Management Sciences, Quetta, Pakistan. Project: Combining Physical and Logical Security to avoid threats in technical areas
2001-2002	Diploma in IT, Balochistan Institute of Information Technology, Quetta, Pakistan.
2002-2002	Diploma in .Net, Balochistan Institute of Information Technology, Quetta, Pakistan.

Research Interests and Publications

- Event detection and evolution using social media streams
- Social computing (Social Network Analysis, Social Media Analytics)
- Big data analytics, machine learning, text mining

Published

Z Saeed, R.A Abbasi, I Razzak. EveSense: What can you sense from Twitter?. *In: Jose J. et al. (eds) Advances in Information Retrieval. ECIR 2020.* Lecture Notes in Computer Science, vol 12036. Springer, Cham (Core Rank: A) (download)

Saeed, Z., Abbasi, R. A., Razzak, M. I., and Xu, G. (2019). Event detection in Twitter stream using weighted dynamic heartbeat graph approach, *IEEE Computational Intelligence Magazine*, 14(3):29-38. (**IF: 9.083, SJR: Q1**) (download)

Saeed, Z., Abbasi, R. A., Razzak, M. I., Maqbool, O., Sadaf, A., and Xu, G. (2019). Enhanced Heartbeat Graph for emerging event detection on Twitter using time series networks, *Expert Systems with Applications*, 136:115-132. (**IF: 5.452, SJR: Q1**) (download)

Saeed, Z., Abbasi, R. A., Maqbool, Sadaf, A., Razzak, I., Ali, D., Aljo-hani, N. R., and Xu, G. (2019). What's happening around the world? A Survey and Framework on event detection techniques on Twitter, *Journal of Grid Computing*, 17(2):279-312. (**IF 2.095, SJR: Q1**) (download)

Farooq G., Iqbal Z., **Saeed Z.** et al, (2020). A Dynamic Three-Bit Image Steganography Algorithm for Medical and e-Healthcare Systems, *IEEE Access*, 8:181893-181903 – (**IF 3.745, SJR: Q1)** (download)

Saeed, Z., Abbasi, R. A., Sadaf, A., Razzak, M. I., and Xu, G. (2018). Text stream to temporal network - A dynamic heartbeat graph to detect emerging events on Twitter. *In Advances in Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining - 22nd Pacific-Asia Conference (PAKDD 2018), Melbourne, Australia*, June 3-6, Lecture Notes in Computer Science, vol 10938. Springer, Cham. (Core Rank: A) (download)

Seemab, U., ul Ain, Q., Nawaz, M. S., **Saeed, Z.**, & Rashid, S. (2012). TrFAST: A Tool to Predict Signaling Pathway-specific Transcription Factor Binding Sites. *Genomics, proteomics & bioinformatics*, 10(6), 354-359. (**IF 6.6, SJR: Q1**) (download)

Saeed Z., Sadaf A., Siraj M. Activity Based Correlation of Documents using Association Rule Mining, 7th IEEE *International Conference on Emerging Technologies (ICET 2011)*, Islamabad, Pakistan pp 1-7 (download)

Under Review

Fazal M.A., Sam F., Andrew J., **Saeed Z.** (2020). Investigating cognitive workload in concurrent speech-based information communication, *International Journal of Human-Computer Studies* - **(Under Review)** - **Impact Factor 3.163**

Hussain K., Abbasi R.A., **Saeed Z.** (2020). Abusive Tweets Detection using Supervised Learning with Contextual Features, *Knowledge-Based Systems* - **(Under Review) - Impact Factor 5.1**

In Progress

Saeed Z., Abbasi R.A., Razzak I., Fazal M.A. (2020). Spectral learning on complex network to detect drifting concept using context-aware sliding windows, *Future Generation Computer Systems* - **(Writing Manuscript) - Impact Factor 5.7**

Fazal M.A., Sam F., Andrew J., **Saeed Z.** (2020). The effects of long-term listening to Concurrent Speech, *Computers in Human Behavior* - (Writing Manuscript) - Impact Factor 5.8

Teaching Experience

09/2020 - Peresnt	Assistant Professor, University of Central Punjab, Lahore, Pakistan Courses: Operating Systems, Emerging Trends in Information Retrieval
09/2018 - 06/2019	Lecturer (Visiting), Quaid-i-Azam University, Islamabad, Pakistan Courses Taught: Intro. to Computer Systems, Problem Solving and Programming, Object Oriented Programming
03/2018 - 06/2018	Casual Academic, University of Technology Sydney, Australia Course Taught: Data Structures and Algorithms
02/2015 - 06/2015	Lecturer (Visiting), Air University, Islamabad, Pakistan Courses Taught: Data Structures, Programming Fundamentals
02/2013 - 01/2015	Lecturer (Visiting), PMAS-Arid Agriculture University, Rawalpindi, Pakistan Courses Taught: Modern Programming Languages, Software Engineering
02/2012 - 01/2013	Lecturer (Visiting), Federal Urdu University of Science Arts and Technology, Islamabad, Pakistan Courses Taught: Visual Programming, Distributed Databases

10/2012 - 02/2013 Lecturer, University of Central Punjab, Lahore, Pakistan

Courses Taught: Data Structures, Discrete Structures

09/2009 - 02/2011 Lecturer (Visiting), Quaid-i-Azam University, Islamabad, Pakistan

Courses Taught: Problem Solving and Programming

Professional Experience

07/2017 - 06/2018 Research Scholar/Software Developer, Advanced Analytics Institute, UTS,

Sydney, Australia (Web)

Responsibilities: Developing novel graph-based method to transform text stream data. Crawling Twitter data using Streaming and Search APIs. Improving performance in event detection process via exploring and designing various

features. Developing a micro-finance application called FinQ.

02/2012 - 10/2012 **Software Engineer,** Diyatech, Islamabad, Pakistan (Web)

Responsibilities: Development, integration and maintenance of software NCache — a performance enhancement Framework for Web Applications

07/2010 - 02/2012 **Software Engineer,** M-Net Technologies, Islamabad, Pakistan (Web)

Responsibilities: Design and development of custom software solutions. Time

and cost estimation, resource allocation and client communication.

04/2006 - 04/2007 **Project Developer,** BUITEMS, Quetta, Pakistan (Web)

Responsibilities: Design and development of security system for computer labs,

testing, training and deployment.

Workshops and Events

- Workshop on "Use of Artificial Intelligence Against COVID-19", organized under China-Pakistan Science Workshop (I) by PASTIC, QAU, Pakistan and BTBU China, held on 23rd July 2020.
- Participated in "INTRODUCTION TO TEACHING FIRST YEAR SUBJECTS", organized by Institute for Interactive Media and Learning, University of Technology Sydney, held on 26th March 2018
- Participated in "ACTIVE LEARNING IN UTSONLINE", organized by Institute for Interactive Media and Learning, University of Technology Sydney, held on 27th March 2018
- Participated in casual academic workshop "TOOLS FOR ONLINE FEEDBACK", organized by Institute for Interactive Media and Learning, University of Technology Sydney, held on 28th March 2018
- Poster Presentation in Faculty of Engineering & IT Research Showcase event, organized by FEIT,
 University of Technology Sydney, held on 14th June, 2018

Technical Skills

Programming Python, C/C++, C#, VB.Net, JAVA

Web-based ASP.Net, PHP, JavaScript, jQuery, AJAX, SOAP/Restful API

Framework .Net, Entity, MVC, Codelgniter, Django

AWS S3, EC2, RDS, ELB, ELC

Development IDEs PyCharm, Visual Studio, NetBeans, Eclipse, PhpStorm

Awards

- Awarded **Student Grant** by 42nd European Conference on Information Retrieval (**ECIR'2020**)
- Award research & development funding for start-up and innovative projects under National Technology Fund by IGNITE (2018).
- Awarded Ph.D. Fellowship by Higher Education Commission (HEC), Islamabad, Pakistan under Indigenous Ph.D. fellowship program Batch-II. (Feb 2013-Jul 2017)
- Awarded research funding for foreign research visit under International Research Support
 Initiative Program (IRSIP) by Higher Education Commission (HEC), Islamabad, Pakistan. (Aug
 2017-Jan 2018)
- Awarded research fellowship by Advanced Analytics Institute, University of Technology Sydney, Australia. (Feb 2018 - July 2018)
- Awarded merit scholarship in M.Phil, Department of Computer Science, Quaid-i-Azam University, Islamabad, Pakistan. (2007-2008)

Community Services

PC Member

- Int. Conference on Behavioral, Economic, and Socio-Cultural Computing (BESC) 2018, Taiwan Invited Reviewer:
 - Pacific Rim International Conference on Artificial Intelligence (PRICAI), 2018, china
 - Int. Conference on Advances in Social Networks Analysis and Mining, (ASONAM), 2018, Spain
 - IEEE International Conference on Big Data Science And Engineering, (BigDataSE), 2018, USA

Reviewing for Journals:

• Expert Systems with Applications, Elsevier